A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Medical Interests, Series K FA320
Rockefeller Archive Center
Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Medical Interests, Series K
1898-1961
Rockefeller Archive Center
Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.)
Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison), 1839-1937
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman
Rockefeller, David
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller, John D., Jr. (John Davison), 1874-1960
FA320
13.3 Cubic Feet
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records are arranged by subject matter in 27 series. Most of these series are wholly or partially open for research. The series are:
A John D. Rockefeller, Sr. C Business Interests D Civic Interests E Cultural Interests F Economic Reform Interests G Educational Interests H Friends and Services I Homes J Housing Interests K Medical Interests L Real Estate M Maps and Memorabilia N Religious Interests O Rockefeller Boards P Welfare - General Files Q World Affairs R Welfare - Youth Files S Documents T Public Relations U Public Land Law Review Commission V Greenrock W Properties X Costume Collection Y Media Z John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal AA Abby Aldrich Rockefeller AC Abby Rockefeller Mauzé
Biographical/Historical note
The central figure in the creation and operation of the Standard Oil Company during its rise to the top of the petroleum industry, John D. Rockefeller (JDR) established for the family a leading role in business and philanthropy. From the days of his earliest employment, Rockefeller, a devout Baptist, was generous in his giving to worthy causes, especially those of a religious nature. During the 1890s he developed an orderly system of philanthropic giving through an office staff that included his close advisor, Frederick T. Gates (1853-1929) and his son, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1874-1960). With the advise of these and other associates, Rockefeller established the University of Chicago, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), the Rockefeller Foundation, and other philanthropic organizations working nationally and internationally in the fields of education, religion, and health. Rockefeller's total donations to philanthropic endeavors are estimated to have been $540 million.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (JDR Jr.) joined his father's office on October 1, 1897. He oversaw the expansion and diversification of the philanthropic work begun by his father. During his lifetime, the younger Rockefeller gave more than $537 million to educational, religious, cultural, medical, and other charitable projects.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and his wife, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (1874-1948), passed the Rockefeller philanthropic impulse on to their children. John D. 3rd (1906-1978), Nelson A. (1908-1979), Laurance S. (1910-2004), Winthrop (1912-1973), and David (1915-) further expanded and diversified Rockefeller influence and interests, establishing their own philanthropic organizations, most notably the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1940), and becoming more active politically.
Scope and Contents note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller (OMR) materials document the increasing role assumed by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in the management of Rockefeller affairs and amply document his business and philanthropic affairs. They also chronicle the entrance of JDR Jr.'s sons, John D. 3rd, Nelson A., Laurance S., Winthrop, and David, into the world of business, philanthropy, civic leadership, and politics as they joined the office.
This material contains correspondence, reports, pamphlets, memoranda, deeds, maps, contracts, reports, minutes, charters, certificates of incorporation, clippings, diaries, notebooks, calendars, and memorabilia.
There is a microfilm card index of personal and institutional names.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 02
Scope and Contents note
The 35 boxes in this series cover the years 1898-1961. The Messrs. Rockefeller, Sr. and Jr., Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Abby Rockefeller Mauze, the five brothers, and their spouses are all represented in this series. Mr. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. 3rd, and Laurance S. Rockefeller are have the most connection to thse records.
The records reflect the Rockefeller family philanthropic policy toward public and private healthcare. Major subjects within the series include birth control and "social hygiene," cancer, health agencies, mental hygiene, polio, tuberculosis, and--the largest section--hospitals.
In the specific topics, such as cancer and polio, the policy on giving was generally based on personal interest or interest generated by the presentation of new lines of research. This sometimes involved expanding existing laboratories and sometimes establishing new laboratories. In either case, established and reputable committees or research facilities were supported and acted as overseers and distribution agents. Two examples of this are the American Cancer Society and the National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis.
In the two broad categories of health agencies and hospitals, the policy was generally one of giving to umbrella organizations on the national, state and local level and letting those organizations distribute the funds. This policy was adopted, in general, to avoid dealing with the hundreds of individual requests and having to make the necessarily subjective decisions involved in each case. The family strongly also believed that the most good could be done with the available funds using this method of distribution.
Despite that established policy, the family was inundated with requests for support from individual hospitals. This part of the series is the largest. The established policy was generally followed except in cases of personal interest or when the family had a residence in the area of a specific hospital. As with specific diseases and health agencies, the hospitals given support were often those that demonstrated leadership in setting medical standards. Many hospitals did receive support by showing acute need, especially those in middle- and low-income areas.
The bulk of the material is composed of routine appeals and correspondence answering those appeals. There are many instances of an agency or hospital being put on the philanthropic program early in the century and routinely sending reports for years after. Declinations were usually based on policy but were sometimes based on a judgment of the personnel involved. In none of these situations was the discussion based on anything except analysis of what was best for the particular cause and not on personalities.
The family continually supported medical training for people of color and medical care in low-income and under-served communities.
The family's interest coincides with a significant period of medical growth and transformation. In many ways the family geared its medical philanthropy to supplement the national trend in modern scientific research that was helped by the opening of the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (later Rockefeller University). Many new lines of research were supported at a time when new methods were in embryonic stages. The most significant files are those related to the "suppression of vice" and the social hygiene movement. These records shed light on the beginnings of one of the most important social movements of the 20th century.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records include: FA310 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Sr.
FA312 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Business Interests
FA313 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests
FA314 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests
FA315 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Economic Reform Interests
FA316 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Educational Interests
FA317 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Friends and Services
FA318 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Homes
FA319 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Housing Interests
FA321 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Real Estate
FA322 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Maps and Memorabilia
FA323 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Religious Interests
FA324 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Rockefeller Boards
FA325 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - General Files
FA326 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs
FA327 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - Youth Files
FA329 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Public Relations
FA333 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Costume Collection
FA334 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Media
FA335 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal
FA336 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller
FA337 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Rockefeller Mauze
World War I; World War II; Public relations; Philanthropy; Housing rehabilitation; Religion; Public welfare; Government policy; Folk art; Health insurance; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; United States; Travel; Urban renewal; Urban policy; Restoration and conservation; Religious institutions; State governments -- United States; Rockefeller family -- Art collections; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Art, Modern; Business; Arts; Capital investments; Business enterprises, Foreign; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Charitable contributions; Family planning; Federal government -- United States; Education; Education -- United States; Economic policy; Economics; Art; Economic development; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); International relations -- United States; Juvenile delinquency; Maternal health services; Medical care; Medical education; Medical research; Medical sciences; New York (N.Y.); Charities; Charities -- Investments; Child welfare; Civic improvement; International cooperation; International economic relations; International education; International relations; Philanthropy -- United States; Political campaigns -- United States; Political science; New York (State); Parks -- New York (State); Performing arts; Prohibition; Public health; Public health administration; Public policy
- Birth Control
  - Birth Control - Birth Control Organizations, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd's interest in birth control movement; discussion of moral, medical and social implications; comments on leading figures and organizations in the field. Emphasis on population control and planned parenthood after 1940. Small contributions to various organizations by members of the family. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Arthur W. Packard, Arthur Woods, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Margaret Sanger.
    File Plan note
    139
  - Birth Control - Birth Control Organizations, 1940-1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Birth Control - Birth Control Organizations, 1948-1957 (Box 1, Folder 0002A)
  - Birth Control - Birth Control Organizations - World Population Conferences, 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Cheltenham, 1948; United Nations, 1954.
  - Birth Control - Birth Control Organizations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Contributions, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Birth Control - National Committee on Maternal Health, 1924-1927, 1932-1944, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 0004A)
    Scientific research into contraception and related fields; appeals to the Bureau of Social Hygiene and the Rockefellers for contributions. Personnel arrangements; policy questions within Committee. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Raymond B. Fosdick, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    139.1
  - Birth Control - National Committee on Maternal Health - By-laws, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd and Arthur W. Packard on committee to revise by-laws. Arthur W. Packard did detail work.
  - Birth Control - National Committee on Maternal Health - Contributions, 1924, 1933-1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Contributions by John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd and Bureau of Social Hygiene toward research and propagation of ideas.
  - Birth Control - National Committee on Maternal Health - Contributions - John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1934-1943, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Several anonymous contributions.
  - Birth Control - American Birth Control League - Contributions, 1924-1938 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Developing plans of the League. Anonymous contribution by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in 1924; direct but anonymous Rockefeller contributions during 1930. Contributions from Bureau of Social Hygiene; small donations from Nelson A. Rockefeller and Laurance S. Rockefeller; some contributions through Planned Parenthood Committee. Correspondents include Margaret Sanger, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Raymond B. Fosdick, Arthur W. Packard.
    139.2
  - Birth Control - American Birth Control League - Contributions - John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1934-1938 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Special contribution for Massachusetts fight.
  - Birth Control - Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau, 1929, 1933-1939 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Margaret Sanger's splinter group which carried on for a while in competition with the older Birth Control League. John D. Rockefeller 3rd is the primary donor. Correspondents include Margaret Sanger.
    139.2A
  - Birth Control - New York Birth Control Federation, 1934-1939 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Reports on work; requests for aid. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    139.3
  - Birth Control - New York Birth Control Federation - Contributions - John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1934-1938 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. annual contribution.
  - Birth Control - New York Birth Control Federation - Contributions - John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1934-1939 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Annual contribution.
  - Birth Control - Population Association of America, 1935-1936, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    To study population trends. Contribution by John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    139.4
  - Birth Control - Population Association of America - Contributions - John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Birth Control - Eugenics Society, 1934-1940 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    English society concerned with birth control problems. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    139.5
  - Birth Control - National Medical Committee on Federal and State Legislation, 1934-1935, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Effort to get federal laws regarding contraceptives repealed. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution. Arthur W. Packard followed committee's activities. Correspondents include Margaret Sanger, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Raymond B. Fosdick, Arthur W. Packard.
    139.6
  - Birth Control - National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control, 1934-1937 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Lobby group advocating changes in birth control laws. Correspondents include Arthur w. Packard, Morris Ernst, Margaret Sanger.
    139.7
  - Birth Control - National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control - Contributions - John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1934-1937 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Birth Control - National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control - Contributions - John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Birth Control - National Committee for Medical Rights in Massachusetts, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Worked in Massachusetts referendum to repeal state anti-contraceptive laws. John D. Rockefeller 3rd contributed. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Arthur W. Packard.
    139.8
  - Birth Control - Maternity Center Association, 1940, 1944-1952 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Reports on work in educational program for parents, obstetrical training for nurses. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    139.9
  - Birth Control - Maternity Center Association - Contributions - Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, 1940-1947 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Birth Control - Maternity Center Association - Contributions - Laurance S. Rockefeller and Nelson A. Rockefeller, 1942-1960 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Birth Control - Population Study - L. Outhwaite - Laurance S. Rockefeller, 1947-1951 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Outhwaite hired by Laurance S. Rockefeller to prepare study of population trends. Delays; supervision. No copy of study in file. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Leonard Outhwaite, Arthur W. Packard, E. B. Young.
    139.10
  - Birth Control - Birthright, Inc. (Human Betterment Association of America), 1944, 1947-1951, 1955-1961 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    Urged selective sterilization. Abby Rockefeller Mauz made first family contribution, 1959; repeated in 1961. John D. Rockefeller 3rd interested in organization's goals, but did not contribute. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Abby Rockefeller Mauz.
    139.11
  - Birth Control - American Committee on Maternal Health, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    Unsuccessful attempt to interest office in work of Committee. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard.
    139.12
  - Birth Control - Population Reference Bureau, 1940, 1954-1955, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    Information center on population problems. Issued "Population Bulletin" and other articles on population growth. Contributions by Abby Rockefeller Mauz. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Abby Rockefeller Mauz.
    139.13
  - Birth Control - World Population Emergency Campaign, 1958-1961 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    Special fund-raising campaign. Tribute to Margaret Sanger on 45th anniversary of her first clinic. No Rockefeller contributions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, William H. Draper, Margaret Sanger.
    139.14
  - Birth Control - World Population Emergency Campaign, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 0029A)
  - Birth Control - Birth Control Federation of America, 1939-1942 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    Consolidation of American Birth Control League and Birth Control Clinic. Plans, program of Federation. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Arthur W. Packard, MArgaret Sanger, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Nelson A. Rockefeller.
    139.21
  - Birth Control - Birth Control Federation of America - Contributions - John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1939-1941 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Birth Control - Planned Parenthood Federation of America
    Background information on organization; routine affairs of Federation. Problems of organization; Margaret Sanger. Arthur W. Packard represented Rockefeller interest. Contributions made by Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Mary French Rockefeller, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé, and Martha Baird Rockefeller throughout the years 1940-1961. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Margaret Sanger, Kenneth Rose, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Dana S. Creel, William Vogt.
    139.22
    - 1940-1946 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - 1947-1949 (Box 4, Folder 33)
      General note
      DR material removed to Folder 33A.
    - 1947-1949 (Box 4, Folder 33A)
    - Not Used (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Not Used (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Not Used (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - 1950-1952 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - 1953-1959 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - 1958-1961 (Box 5, Folder 39A)
      Conditions Governing Access note
      Restricted material.
  - Birth Control - International Planned Parenthood Federation, 1948, 1951-1956 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    Policies and program of Federation; family interest in international program. Contributions by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondents include Margaret Sanger, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Martha Baird Rockefeller.
    139.23
  - Birth Control - International Planned Parenthood Federation, 1957-1961 (Box 5, Folder 41)
- Cancer
  - Cancer - American Cancer Society - General Correspondence, 1913, 1915-1929 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    Formerly American Society for the Control of Cancer. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $125,000 in 1926 toward endowment, plus $15,000 to complete $1,000,000 campaign. Contribution record; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made largest annual contribution by any individual. Thomas M. Debevoise a member of Society. Contributions by John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Thomas M. Debevoise, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    136
  - Cancer - American Cancer Society - General Correspondence, 1930-1931, 1937-1961 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Cancer - American Cancer Society - Westchester County Committee, 1930-1932, 1940-1941, 1946-1947, 1949, 1951-1953, 1957, 1959-1961 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    Small gifts.
  - Cancer - New York City Cancer Committee, 1930-1935, 1940-1950 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    Subject of individual family giving until 1947, after which Rockefeller Brothers Fund made regular contributions and family declined most requests. Small small gifts made; Laurance S. Rockefeller stock gift; others, 1950-1961. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Martha Baird Rockefeller.
  - Cancer - New York City Cancer Committee, 1951-1961 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    Subject of individual family giving till 1947, after which Rockefeller Brothers Fund made regular contributions and family declined most requests. Small small gifts made; Laurance S. Rockefeller stock gift; others, 1950-1961. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Martha Baird Rockefeller.
  - Cancer - Miscellaneous, 1933, 1937-1949 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    Suggested cancer cures, crackpot and otherwise. Requests for aid, declined.
    136.1
  - Cancer - Miscellaneous, 1950-1959 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Cancer - Miscellaneous, 1960-1961 (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - Cancer - National Cancer Foundation, 1946-1949, 1956-1961 (Box 7, Folder 50)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller contributions. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Mrs. Frank Washburn.
    136.2
- Health Agencies
  - Health Agencies - American Public Health Association, 1919-1932, 1937, 1944, 1949, 1954-1956 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    To improve medical conditions at local level. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. becomes sustaining member at $50.00 a year, 1919; increased gifts to $100 in 1925; discontinued in 1930. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. served on special committee in New York City for American Public Health Association (APHA) convention. Raymond B. Fosdick article from "American Journal of Public Health," November 1944. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s letter to Dr. Albert Gregg (recipient of Lasker Award). Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    137
  - Health Agencies - Citizen's Health Committee on Neighborhood Health Development, 1941-1943, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 52)